interviewer:नमस्कार बाबा
----
interviewer:Hello Baba
baba: नमस्कार
----
baba: Hello
interviewer: हर हर महादेव
baba: हर हर महादेव
----
Interviewer: Har Har Mahadev baba: Har Har Mahadev
interviewer:बाबा छोटा सा एक अपना परिचय दे दीजिये, कि आपका नाम क्या है, क्या करते हैं, ये कौन सी जगह है, हम कहाँ हैं ?
----
Interviewer: Baba, please introduce yourself a little, what is your name, what do you do, which place is this, where are we?
baba: आप अभी काशी में बात कर रहे हैं मुझसे, इस जगह को काशी बोलते हैं, और इसे काशी क्यों बोलते हैं ?
----
baba: You are talking to me in Kashi right now, this place is called Kashi, and why is it called Kashi?
यहाँ हमारे तीनो लोक के दाता, प्रदाता, जो भी आप बोलते हो, जिस भी ढंग से आप उन्हें मानते हो, जो भी नाम आप दे सकते हो
----
Here the giver, the provider of our three worlds, whatever you say, whatever way you believe in Him, whatever name you can give,
उन्होंने अपना कदम यहाँ रख दिया, इसलिए इसे काशी कहा गया, ये मुक्ति का एक धाम बन गया
----
He placed his foot here, hence it was called Kashi, it became an abode of salvation.
यहाँ पर बड़े-बड़े राजा लोग आए, अपने देश से, अपने अपने महल बनाए, यहाँ पर कुछ दिन रहे, अपनी मुक्ति के लिए कुछ साधना भी की
----
Big kings and people came here from their countries, built their own palaces, stayed here for a few days, and also did some meditation for their salvation.
अच्छी-अच्छी चीज़ें, जो भी उनके समझ में आया, जो पहले का हिसाब किताब था उनका उसके हिसाब से वो चले गए
----
All the good things, whatever they understood, according to the earlier accounts, they went away.
उनकी वजह से आज यहाँ पर ये सादा वातावरण बदला हुआ और पूरी भीडभाड वाला हो गया
----
Because of them, today this simple environment here has changed and become completely crowded.
और कुछ अपनी श्रद्धा से आते हैं, पहले कुछ ऐसे श्रद्धालु थे यहाँ जो जब अपने घरों से निकलते थे उससे पहले कई महीनो से अन्न-जल नहीं लेते थे
----
And some come out of their devotion, earlier there were some devotees here who did not take food or water for many months before leaving their homes.
कोई तो जल भी नहीं पीता था दस दस दिन पंद्रह दिन कि जाएंगे काशी में तो वहीँ अन्न जल लेंगे और जहाँ पर हमारी मुक्ति का भी कुछ काम हो जाएगा
----
Some people did not even drink water. If we go to Kashi for ten to fifteen days, we will take food and water there and some work for our salvation will also be done.
और कुछ हमें मिल भी जाएगा, और ये काशी इसलिए है कि जो जन्म हमें मिलता है इंसान का
----
We will also get something else, and this is Kashi because the birth we get is of a human being.
इंसान का जो तन मिला है हमें ये, एक बार यहाँ बुलाकर मौका इसलिए देता है कि अगर आप आकर अपने कुछ कर्मों को कमाना चाहते हो, तो यहाँ आकर कमा लो
----
This human body that we have got, calls us here once and gives us an opportunity so that if you want to come and earn some of your karma, then come here and earn it.
लें वो कर्म अब कोई कमाता नहीं है
interviewer: क्यों
baba: अब लूगों का कुछ काम ऐअसा हो गया, धन का आराम ऐसा हो गया
----
Take that karma, no one earns it now
interviewer: why
baba: Now some of the work of the people has become like this, the comfort of money has become like this.
कि जो पूरा वातावरण है वो पूरा ही अलग ढंग से चलने लगा
----
That the whole environment started moving in a different way.
और पैसे का इतना ज्यादा काम हो गया घर में कि कमाई से भी ज्यादा काम होने लगा
----
And there was so much money involved in the house that there was more work than earning.
समझ रहे हो  मेरी बात
----
Do you understand what I am saying?
कि ये वातावरण सब बदल गया है अब
----
that this environment has all changed now
interviewer: बाबा एक मिनट कुछ प्रॉब्लम आ रही है
----
Interviewer: Baba, I am facing some problem just a minute.
interviewer discussing some issues with the camera
----
बाबा इतने सालों में आपने बहुत बड़ा जीवन अपना...
baba: सारा जीवन
----
Baba, you have lived a big life in so many years...
baba: whole life
interviewer: तो एक मिनट, आपने काशी को बदलते हुए देखा है,तो उसके बारे में बताइए कि कैसे बदला है
----
Interviewer: So one minute, you have seen Kashi changing, so tell me how it has changed.
baba: देखिए, काशी एक ऐसी जगह थी जो आप राजा हरिश्चंद्र घाट देख रहे हैं, वो स्वयं भगवान् ही थे
----
baba: See, Kashi was such a place that you are seeing Raja Harishchandra Ghat, he was God himself.
वो मृत्युलोक में जब आए, ये जो रामायण, जो भी कथाएँ बनाई गई मृत्युलोक में, ये सब आपको हमें, हम सबको इसी से सीख लेने के लिए बनाया गया
----
When he came to the mortal world, this Ramayana, whatever stories were created in the mortal world, all these were created for you, us, all of us to learn from this.
बाकी उनको कोई जरूरत नहीं थी, कोई आवश्यकता नहीं थी, वो तीनों काल के मालिक हैं और वो जो भी चाहें स्वयं से कर सकते हैं
----
The rest he had no need, no need, he is the master of all three times and can do whatever he wants with himself.
समझ रहे हैं
----
are you understanding
और इस पूरे विश्व में ऐसे कोई नहीं नहीं गया जैसे हरिश्चंद्र गए
----
And no one in this entire world has gone like Harishchandra did.
अपने तन से गया, ऐसे कोई यहाँ से आज तक गया नहीं
----
He left with his own body, no one has ever left like this before.
आया जरूर था अपना तन लेकर, लेकिन गया नहीं, अपना तन भी यहीं छोड़ गया
----
He definitely came with his body, but did not go, he too left his body here only
ये सबसे बड़ी काशी की खासियत है
interviewer: अभी कैसा हो गया काशी
----
This is the biggest specialty of Kashi
Interviewer: How is Kashi now?
अब तो देखिए अगर सरकार न करे तो कुछ हो भी नहीं, आपको अगर कुछ मौज मस्ती नहीं मिलेगी तो आप उस जगह की कदर भी नहीं करेंगे
----
Now see, if the government doesn't do anything then nothing will happen, if you don't get some fun then you won't even appreciate that place.
बस उसी चीज़ से पूरा वातावरण बदलने लगा, तो जब साड़ी मौज मस्तियाँ लिमिट में थी तो सब सही था अब लिमिट से ज्यादा होने लगी तो कब्ज़े से बाहर होने लगा
----
Just because of that thing, the whole atmosphere started changing, then when all the fun and enjoyment was within the limit, everything was fine, now when it started exceeding the limit, it started going out of control.
और ये तो होना ही है, जो लिमिट वाला काम चलता है फिर वो बिना लिमिट के चलने की तरफ कुछ ज्यादा ही चलने लगता है
----
And this is bound to happen, the work that works with limits then starts moving a little more towards working without limits.
लेकिन ये सारी चीज़ें उसने बताई हैं, हमने खुद ही बिगाड़ा है हम खुद ही सही करेंगे, सब कुछ स्वयं करेंगे
----
But he has told all these things, we have spoiled it ourselves, we will correct it ourselves, we will do everything ourselves.
अब यहाँ वो कुछ नहीं करेंगे, हमको आपको ही सारा काम करना है
----
Now they won't do anything here, we you have to do all the work.
हमारे ही हाथ से आपका पुण्य भी होगा और पाप भी होगा
----
Your good deeds and sins will also be done by our hands.
ये धन देखिए जिस वातावरण से आपके घर में धन आता है, उसी वातावरण से आपके परिवार की श्रृष्टि होती है
----
Look at this wealth. The environment from which wealth comes to your house is the same environment from which your family is created.
उसी तरह वो भी भागता है
----
he also runs the same way
आप देख लीजिये चाहे छोटे से चाहे बड़े से, अगर कहीं कम है तो कम की तरफ वाली रफ़्तार में है
----
You see whether it is small or big, if it is less somewhere then it is in the direction of less.
लेकिन देखा देखि जिस हिसाब से चल रही है, पहले ऐसा नहीं था, पहले लोग ये नहीं देखते थे कि हमारे साइड वाला क्या खा रहा है
----
But the way it is going, it was not like this earlier, earlier people did not see what the person on our side was eating.
अगर वो ये चीज़ खा रहा है, तो हमको ये चीज़ चाहिए
----
If he's eating this thing, we need this thing
वो समझ लेता था इसके किस्मत में ये ठीक है, हमारी किस्मत में ये ठीक नहीं है
----
He used to understand that this is good in his luck, this is not good in our luck.
इसलिए हम उको जाने दें, लेकिन अब ऐसा नहीं है, अब वो उसको पाने की कोशिश करता है
----
So we let him go, but not anymore, now he tries to get that thing
वो कोशिश भी इतनी नाकाम हो जाती है कि आदमी सब कुछ करने को तैयार हो जाता है
----
That effort also fails so much that the man becomes ready to do anything.
बाबा: यही बदलते हुए देखा है
interviewer: क्या बदल गया लोगों में इर्ष्या, जलन ?
----
Baba: This is what I have seen changing.
Interviewer: Has jealousy and envy changed in people?
baba:बस यही देखा देखी चल रही है, वो अगर इतना कर रहा है तो हमको क्यूँ नहीं मिल रहा
----
baba: Just seeing this, if he is doing so much then why are we not getting it?
अब सबको थोडा सा अगर अच्छा कपडा नहीं मिले, अगर आपके साइड वाले ने दस हज़ार की साडी पहनी है उया दस हज़ार की आपने पेंट ली है
----
Now if everyone does not get good clothes, if the person next to you is wearing a saree worth ten thousand or you have bought a pant worth ten thousand.
और आपके दोस्त ने अगर वो नहीं ली है तो उसे थोड़ी सी दिक्कत हो जाएगी
----
And if your friend has not taken it then he will face a little problem.
चाहे वो आपका कितना भी करीब हो जाए
----
no matter how close he gets to you
और सबसे बड़ा जो रिश्ता होता है
----
And the biggest relationship is
रिश्ता जो साक्षात कृष्ण भगवान् ने अर्जुन को  खुद समझाया है
----
The relationship which Lord Krishna himself has explained to Arjun
बोले की ये जो रिश्ते हैं, मरने के बाद तुम्हारे खुद के रिश्तेदार ही तुम्हें घर से बाहर निकाल देते हैं, दो मिनट का समय भी नहीं लगता
----
He said that these are the relationships, after death your own relatives throw you out of the house, it doesn't even take two minutes.
दो मिनट भी नहीं लगते और लोग कुछ दिन शोक प्रकट करते थे
----
It didn't even take two minutes and people would mourn for a few days
अब उस शोक की जगह कुछ आदमी नशे को जगह देने लगे, ये बदल गया
----
Now in place of that grief, some people started giving place to addiction, this changed.
पहले ऐसा नहीं था, नशे का कुछ जरिया नहीं था, अब नशे का एक एक आदि है
----
Earlier it was not like this, there were no sources of intoxication, now there is a source of intoxication.
आपको जैसे हर घर में दवा की जरूरत है तो हर घर में नशेडी की भी है
----
Just as there is a need for medicine in every house, there is also a drug addict in every house.
पहले हर घर में नशेडी नहीं थे
----
Earlier there were not drug addicts in every house
अगर एक कोई घर में हो जाता था तो चार घरवाले उसे ताना मारकर सुधार देते थे
----
If someone was wrong in the house, four members of the house would taunt him and correct him.
उसे सही रास्ते पर ला देते थे लेकिन अब ऐसा नहीं है
----
Used to bring him on the right path but now it is not so
अब तो अगर हम किसी को सही रास्ता बताएंगे तो हमसे बड़ा कोई गलत आदमी नहीं है
----
Now, if we show someone the right path, then no person is more wrong than us.
interviewer: सही रास्ता क्या है बाबा
----
Interviewer: Baba, what is the right path?
सही रास्ता जो मैं आपको बोल रहा हूँ, आपको जो भी चीज़ प्रिय है, मैं आपको सब करने के लिए बोलूँगा, और जहाँ रुकावट डालेंगे वो सबसे प्रिय हो जाएगा
----
The right path that I am telling you, whatever you love, I will tell you to do everything, and where you put obstacles will become the most loved.
वही रास्ता बिगड़ रहा है, वो बात आपको समझ में नहीं आ रही है, और आप थोड़े में ही अपना सब कुछ खो रहे हो
----
That path is deteriorating, you are not able to understand that thing, and you are losing everything in a short time.
सबसे बड़ी कर्म की कमाई है, ये तन मिलना कर्म की ही बड़ी कमाई है
----
This is the biggest earning of karma, getting this body is the biggest earning of karma.
बड़े कर्मों से मिलता है, ऐसे ही नहीं मिलता क्योंकि आपको जिसने उसने मशीन बनाकर यहाँ बैठाया है, आपने भी इतनी ही बड़ी मशीन बनाई
----
You get it through great deeds, you don't get it just like that, because the one who made you a machine and made you sit here, you also made an equally big machine.
आप जो हैं बादल में भी हवाई जहाज़ उड़ाने लगे, आप आकाशवाणी बनाने लगे, और बताने लगे कि आज भारिश होगी, आज हवा तेज़ चलेगी
----
You, who are you, started flying airplanes even in the clouds, you started making airwaves, and started telling that it will rain today, today the wind will blow strong.
आप इतनी जानकारी अपनी मशीन से लेने लगे तो वैसे ही आपने जो अपनी मशीन बनाई है
----
If you start taking so much information from your machine, then the machine you have created is the same.
आपके अन्दर उसने मशीन बनाई है, जब वो मशीन आपके अन्दर की काम करती है तब ही ये मशीन को आप बना सकते हो
----
He has made a machine inside you, only when that machine works inside you, you can make this machine.
ये सही रास्ता होता है, लेकिन आज देखिए, अभी किसी को बोलो वो कहेगा बहुत टेंशन है, अरे टेंशन है तो क्या दारु पीने से ख़त्म हो जाएगी ?
----
This is the right path, but see today, tell anyone now, he will say that there is a lot of tension, hey, if there is tension, will it go away by drinking alcohol?
क्या सिगरेट पीने से ख़त्म हो जाएगी? टेंशन को हल करना बहुत ज़रूरी है
----
Will it end by smoking cigarettes? It is very important to resolve tension
सही वजह से अगर उस टेंशन को सही तरह से हल करना चाहेगा तो हल भी नहीं कर पाएगा क्योंकि संख्या न करनेवालों की ज्यादा है
----
If one wants to solve that tension properly for the right reasons, it will not be able to solve it because the number of those who do not do so is more.
और हल करने वाली संख्या बहुत कम हो गई, बिलकुल थोड़ी सी गिनती के बराबर हो गई
----
And the number of solutions became very small, down to just a tiny count.
इसलिए कहाँ चल पाएगा, कहाँ हम आपको ले पाएंगे, आप नहीं चल पाएंगे, कहना बहुत आसान है पर करना बहुत मुश्किल है
----
So where will you be able to walk, where will we be able to take you, you will not be able to walk, it is very easy to say but very difficult to do.
interviewer:अब कुछ नहीं बदलेगा सब खराब हो चुका है ?
----
Interviewer: Nothing will change now, is everything spoiled?
baba: ये सब अपने आप अब कलयुग ने अपना असर दिखाया है, और आप उनके असर में हैं, समझे
----
baba: All this automatically, now Kaliyuga has shown its effect, and you are under its influence, understand.
कलयुग ने अपना असर दिखाया है, कलयुग की वाणी है (someone interrupted from behind and a cross talk is going on in last few seconds)
----
Kaliyuga has shown its effect, Kaliyuga speaks (someone interrupted from behind and a cross talk is going on in last few seconds)
ये कलयुग का असर है और कलयुग अपना असर दिखा रहा है
----
This is the effect of Kalyug and Kalyug is showing its effect.
और कुछ नहीं है
----
there is nothing else
हमारे से ही पाप है हमारे से ही पुण्य है, सब कुछ हमारे से ही है
----
Sin is from us, virtue is from us, everything is from us
interviewer: बाबा ये साधु का जीवन कैसा होता है ?
----
Interviewer: Baba, what is the life of a saint like?
baba: साधू का जीवन सबसे बड़ा वही है जो बताया है आपको कि अगर सच्चा भगत है तो उसका इस धरती से कोई वास्ता नहीं होना चाहिए
----
baba: The greatest life of a saint is the one which I have told you that if he is a true devotee then he should have no connection with this earth.
ये नहीं कि आप किसी आश्रम का सहारा ले रहे हो, या किसी और चीज़ का सहारा लेकर आप खा रहे हो और जी रहे हो और अपना हिसाब किताब बनाया है
----
It is not that you are taking the support of any ashram, or taking the support of anything else, you are eating and living and have made your accounts.
ये कोई बात नहीं है
----
it doesn't matter
असली भगत वही है उसका कि हर चीज़ उसको रोज़ ढूंढनी पड़ती है, हम यहीं काशी के हैं, हमने ये जो हैं, इतने उखड़वाए हैं इन लोगों से
----
The real devotee is the one who has to search for everything every day, we are from Kashi here, we have uprooted so much of who we are from these people.
कि हमारे बाल नीचे पैर तक थे लेकिन लोगों ने उखाड़ - उखाड़कर इतने से कर दिए
----
That our hairs were down to our feet but people uprooted them and made it look like this
तो कुछ तो रह गए पर कुछ नहीं रहे, ये बाते कहनी नहीं चाहिए, ये हमारी जन्मभूमि है और हमारे देश के साथ-साथ विदेश के आदमी यहाँ आते हैं
----
So some remained but some did not, these things should not be said, this is our birthplace and people from our country as well as from abroad come here.
लेकिन ये ऐसा करते हैं
----
but they do this
ये सही आदमी को रहने नहीं देते हैं, इनके साथ जब तुम ढंग से रहोगे तब सुखी रह सकोगे
----
They don't let the right person live, when you live with them properly then you will be happy.
अब हमारा तो ये कर्म है, न तुमसे लड़ सकते हैं न कुछ कर सकते हैं, दोनों तरफ से परेशान हैं
----
Now this is our karma, we can neither fight with you nor do anything, we are troubled from both the sides.
लेकिन हम परेहान इसलिए हैं कि तुम जानते नहीं हो कि कुछ हमारे जैसे ही हैं जिनकी वजह से
----
But we are troubled because you do not know that there are some like us who are keeping..
इस धरती का विनाश रुका हुआ है
----
The destruction of this earth on hold
अगर हमारे जैसे नहीं होते न तो इस धरती का कब का नास हो गया होता, लेकिन अभी कुछ हैं, बचे हुए हैं, लेकिन न तो उनको आप समझ सकते हो
----
If there were no people like us, this earth would have been destroyed long ago, but now there are some, they are left, but neither can you understand them.
न आपके पास इतना समय है, क्योंकि आपका समय जन्म से बस खाने में लगा है, बस आपकी हवस में लगा है, आप उसी में बस लगे रहोगे और चले जाओगे
----
Neither do you have that much time, because since birth your time is busy only in eating, only in your lust, you will just remain busy in that and go away.
आपसे कोई मतलब नहीं बस हमको छोडो
----
I don't care about you, just leave us
इसके बाद अब आप समझ जाइए, ख़त्म कर दीजिए, ज्यादा बोलना सही नहीं है
----
After this, now you understand, finish it, it is not right to speak too much.
interviewer: इसके ऊपर नहीं बात करेंगे किसी और चीज़ के ऊपर बात करेंगे, बाबा काशी के बारे में बताइए कहते हैं कि यहाँ मौत को भी जश्न की तरह मनाया जाता है क्योंकि यह भी भगवान् का ही निर्णय है और आत्मा के बारे में बताइए कि आत्मा कहाँ जाती है ?
----
Interviewer: We will not talk about this, we will talk about something else, tell us about kashi . they says that here even death is celebrated as a celebration because it is also God's decision and tell us about the soul that the soul, Where does it go?
baba: वही आत्मा, उस आत्मा के लिए ही यहाँ जश्न मनाया जाता है
----
baba: That soul, it is for that soul only that the celebration is celebrated here.
क्योंकि ये ऐसी जगह है, ऐसा स्थान है जहाँ जिसने अपने पैर रख दिए, तो यहाँ उसकी आत्मा को सुकून मिल जाएगा
----
Because this is such a place, such a place where whoever sets his feet here, his soul will find peace.
आप ये मिटटी छोड़कर के कहीं और, अपने गाँव में मर गए, अपने देश में मर गए
----
You left this soil and died somewhere else, in your village, in your country.
तो आत्मा को उतनी शान्ति नहीं मिलेगी जितनी इस मिटटी से मिलेगी, इसीलिए इस मिट्टी का नाम काशी रखा गया है
----
So the soul will not get as much peace as it will get from this soil, that is why this soil has been named Kashi.
इसलिए हमारे तुम्हारे कर्मों को सुधारने का एक मौका रखा है उसने इस धरती पर
----
That's why he has given us an opportunity to correct our deeds on this earth.
की कर्म को कमाकर फिर हम वापस कुछ बनकर आएं
----
That after earning our karma, we come back as something.
समझ रहे हो
----
do you understand
interviewer: तो हिन्दू धर्म में काशी की बहुत मान्यता है ?
baba: हाँ, ये है
----
Interviewer: So Kashi has a lot of importance in Hindu religion? baba: Yes, it is
baba: हिन्दू धर्म में जो सबसे बड़ी विशेषता की बात है वो ये है कि कोई धर्म देख लीजिये आप उठाकर
----
baba: The biggest specialty of Hindu religion is that you can look at any religion.
इसमें ही है की जिसने एक भी कर्म धर्म से आगे आकर न किया हो, बाकी की तो बात छोड़ ही दीजिये आप
----
It is only in this that one who has not done even a single action ahead of religion, leave aside the rest.
बाकी बात तो छोड़ दीजिए, इससे बड़ा क्या है जो स्वयं भगवान् आकर यहाँ रहे और उनके लिए उड़नखटोला आया आकाश से और वो उसमें चले गए
----
Leave aside the rest, what is bigger than God himself coming and staying here and a flying thing came for him from the sky and he went in it.
ऐसा कोई दूसरा पूरे विश्व में है? इसीलिए ये काशी है | इसीलिए उनकी जन्नत है
----
Is there anyone else like it in the whole world? That is why this is Kashi. That's why it is their heaven
यहाँ तुम्हारे बहुत से पाप को माफ़ कर दिया जाता है, आप सोचते हैं एक बार गंगा नहाने से कितने पापों से मुक्ति मिल सकती है ?
----
Here many of your sins are forgiven, do you think how many sins can be liberated by taking a bath in Ganga once?
आप जितना अपने मन को स्वच्छ करके नाहा लें, उतने पाप धुल जाएंगे आपके, पर मन स्वच्छ नहीं हो पाता है आपका और पाप साथ ही चले जाते हैं
----
The more you clean your mind and take a bath, the more your sins will be washed away, but your mind is not clean and your sins go away along with you.
आप अपने मन को स्वच्छ कर लीजिए बस, जय हो
----
You just clear your mind, Jai Ho